Guide to the Basil Duke Henning Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Basil Duke Henning papers
1934-1978
MS 834
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.5
Correspondence, writings, research and office files, and teaching materials reflecting Basil Duke Henning's career at Yale University and his service as master of Saybrook College from 1934 to 1978. The correspondence is largely with other historians on professional matters. Among the writers are Henry Horowitz, Douglas Lacey and Caroline Robbins. Included in the papers is a typed draft of: Members of Parliament, 1660-1690 (1963). Other papers relate to his service on various Yale University committees.
Henning, Basil Duke
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from Basil Duke Henning's office, 1978.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials in Box 4 are closed until 2054 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
Scope and Contents
The Basil Duke Henning Papers date from 1934 to 1978 and deal primarily with Henning's career as an historian and his service as a Yale master. Included among the papers are correspondence with other historians, files on the publication of Crises in English History, 1066-1945, and material relating to Yale University committees of which Henning was a member.
The papers were transferred to Manuscripts and Archives from Professor Henning's office in Sterling Memorial Library in June and July of 1978.
Biographical / Historical
Basil Duke Henning received his B.A. degree from Yale University in 1932 and his Ph.D. in 1937. In 1935 he became an instructor in history at Yale and was appointed a Sterling Fellow in History, the Arts and Letters from 1939 to 1940. Henning became an assistant professor in 1945 and the following year an associate professor. From 1971 until his retirement in 1978, he was Colgate Professor of English history. Henning served as Master of Saybrook College from 1946 to 1975.
Educators; Historians; Henning, Basil Duke; Horowitz, Henry, 1923-; Lacey, Douglas R. (Douglas Raymond), 1913-; Robbins, Caroline; Saybrook College (Yale University); Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University -- History; Yale University. Department of History
- Inventory
  - Correspondence with historians
    - A-Z, 1941-1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 1 - 3)
    - Horowitz, Henry, 1964-1976, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Lacey, Douglas, 1960-1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Robbins, Caroline, 1955-1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence with Almet Jenks regarding Cole Porter, 1954 November 10-December 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence regarding Ted Lewis archive, 1970 February 24-March 6 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Conference on British Studies, 1952-1974, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - English universities, printed matter, 1966-1967, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Conference on the "Use of Quantitative Methods in the Study of the History of Legislative Behavior", 1972 March 13-15 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities, project evaluations, 1974-1977 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - "The evolution towards a committee of the whole house during the reign of Elizabeth", 1934 January (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Book reviews, 1935-1974, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Publication of Crises in English History, 1947-1963 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Revisions in publications, 1949-1973 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Publications file, including correspondence, sales data, and book adoption lists, 1947-1965 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Publication agreements and royalty statements, 1947-1977 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Yale Parliamentary Diaries project, 1966-1976, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Yale University, British history search committee, 1973-1976, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Yale University, faculty members in the Korean War, 1950 July 24-September 14, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Yale University, committee on residential college deanships, 1965-1975, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Yale University, Yale College policy coordination committee and committee on university problems, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Yale University Dramatic Association advisory board, 1940-1974, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Yale 1932 class reunion, 1961-1962, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Yale Whiffenpoofs, correspondence on crest, anniversaries, Whiffenpoof tent, etc., 1966-1974, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Letter from H. A. Robinson regarding Dr. Clements Fry's study of students in Yale's residential colleges, 1949 December 29 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Letters commemorating Henning's 29 years as master of Saybrook College, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 27a)
  - RESTRICTED
    Conditions Governing Access
    Materials restricted until January 1, 2054 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
    - Graduate history course grades, 1972-1978 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Recommendations for scholarships, fellowships, and other positions, 1949-1966, undated (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Yale University-Clare College (Cambridge) Mellon fellowships, 1949-1972, undated (Box 4, Folder 30)